Guide to the Planners for Equal Opportunity records, 1964-1978
Planners for Equal Opportunity records, 1964-1978
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Planners for Equal Opportunity Records, 1964-1978
3943
Planners for Equal Opportunity.
3 cubic ft.
Records, newsletters, correspondence, and constitutions.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Planners for Equal Opportunity was established in 1964 by a small group of professionals in the housing, planning, architecture and social work fields as an organization through which planning skills and concepts could be used to work for equality among minorities. The group encouraged professional planners to serve as civil rights advocates and to work for the change of policies and practices they considered racist.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Planners for Equal Opportunity was established in 1964 by a small group of professionals in the housing, planning, architecture and social work fields as an organization through which planning skills and concepts could be used to work for equality among minorities. The group encouraged professional planners to serve as civil rights advocates and to work for the change of policies and practices they considered racist. It published a periodic newsletter, Equalop, which ceased publication in 1971. At its zenith the organization had over 700 members in the United States and Canada with chapters in several regional and urban areas. Under the Planners for Equal Opportunity banner, advocacy planning was conceived, nurtured and to a limited degree, legitimized. The organized disbanded in 1976.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes records of conferences and policy and steering committees; newsletters; correspondence; constitutions; and administrative records. Also includes correspondence of the group's executive director, Walter Thabit.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Planners for Equal Opportunity.; Thabit, Walter.
Subjects:
City planning.; Regional planning.; Equality.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
See also the Walter Thabit Papers, #4215.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Conference Material
Box 1
Series II. PEO Policy and Steering Committee
Box 1
Series III. PEO Miscellaneous
Box 2
Series IV. Equalop Newsletter
Box 2
Series V. Correspondence
Box 2
Series VI. Constitution
Box 2
Series VII. PEO - Administrative
Box 3
Series VIII. Policy Committee
Box 3
Series IX. PEO Program Framework
Box 3
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Conference Material
  - PEO - 3rd Annual Conference, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - PEO Conference materials, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - PEO billings, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 6th Annual Conference, April 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - PEO Conference, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - PEO - 3rd Annual Meeting, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cincinnati Conference, ASPO, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - PEO, 4th Annual, April 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - PEO 4th Annual Meeting Conference Archives, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - PEO Resolutions to AIP, Pittsburgh, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - PEO Pittsburgh, October 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Information sheets (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Conference, March 16, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - PEO Conference proceedings, March 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Washington Conference mailing list, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - PEO AIP Conference, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - AIP Conference, October 1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - War Against the Cities, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - PEO positions and resolutions, AIP Conference, Vietnam petition, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Joint AIP-PEO Committee on Minorities, 1967, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Draft AIP platform/PEO, revised March 5, 1969, January 31, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - October 3 Resolutions, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - AIP election campaign - biographical data; PEO platform, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - PEO/AIP, 1968, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - AIP revolt, 1968, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Series II. PEO Policy and Steering Committees
  - PEO IV, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Policy/Steering Committees, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Minutes - Steering Committee, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Minutes - Policy Committee, 1969, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - PEO Chairman's notes - File, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Washington PEO - Conference press coverage (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Chairman's File - PEO, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - President's File - PEO, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - PEO President's File, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - PEO Policy/Steering Committees, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - PEO Policy/Steering Committees, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - PEO Policy/Steering Committees, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Series III. PEO Miscellaneous
  - PEO-ADVO Case #1, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - PEO - Advocacy jobs file, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - PEO archives material, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Archives material, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - PEO - Miscellaneous, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - PEO - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series IV. Equalop Newsletter
  - Vol. 1, No.1, Spring, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Vol. 1, No. 2, Summer, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Vol. 1, No.3, Winter, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Vol. 1, No. 4, Spring and Summer, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Vol. 1, No. 5, Spring, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Vol. 2, No. 2, Fall, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Vol. 2, No.3, Winter, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Vol. 2, No. 4, Spring, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Vol. 3, No. 1, Summer, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Vol. 3, No. 2, Fall, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Vol. 3, No. 3, Winter, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Vol. 3, No. 4, Spring, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Vol. 4, No. 1, Summer, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Vol. 4, No. 2, 3 & 4, Spring, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Vol. 5, No. 1, 2 & 3, Winter, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Equalop (material) (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Series V. Correspondence
  - 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - 1968 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 1973, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - PEO requests, 1966-1971 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - PEO correspondence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - PEO - Material to review, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - PEO newsletter material, 1966, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Equalop correspondence and background material, 1966, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Series VI. Constitution
  - Constitution PEO, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - PEO - Mailing (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - PEO mailing list, November 1967 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - PEO letterheads, envelopes, membership cards (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - PEO - Library requests (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Steering Committee meeting notice (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - PEO Constitution, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Purposes (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Series VII. PEO - Administrative
  - PEO Treasurer, 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - PEO Foundation, 1969-1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - PEO Pending, 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Materials for Executive Secretary, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Done, 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - PEO Organizing (chapters) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chapter contracts, 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Potential interested organizations, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - PEO mailing, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - PEO - Solicitations, 1964-1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - PEO - Reproduction, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Conference call layout, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series VIII. Policy Committee
  - PEO elections, 1967-1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - PEO Policy Committee ballot, March 16 positions, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Program outline, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Policy statement, August 1968 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - PEO Policy Committee meeting, May 25-26, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Letter to Policy Committee member, December 23, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - PEO Policy Committee, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - PEO Conclave, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - PEO Internal, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Series IX. PEO Program Framework
  - PEO Funding proposal - 10 cities background, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - PEO - 10 cities, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - PEO Model Cities proposal, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Tenants Rights proposal, 1966, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - PEO in Pittsburgh, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Hartman case, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - PEO consultants list, Undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Press release scoring lack of C.P.D. minorities, February 17, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Blueprint for Integrated Education, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - PEO - Letter to Mrs. Flatow (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - ALPA report, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - PEO Advocacy cases requests, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Crisis in rent control, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Communities of Tomorrow, Town & Country Alliance, 1967, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - 10 Cities proposal, Summer, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Harlem TV programs, c. 1970 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - PEO requests file, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - PEO Program Committee, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Nixon Administration Urban problem report card, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Local planning - Local controls press release, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Press release, April 6, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Harvard Urban Field Service, Hartman, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - 1st Annual Conference - Proceedings, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Rent control fact sheet #7, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - 4th Annual Conference, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Resolutions for ASPO, Actions, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Dues schedule, Undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - 1969 PEO Policy Committee reports and minutes (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Women and Planning, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Jobs for Advocates, Undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Covering letter for demand for Planning Services, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Special Award: Hartman, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Release, April 15, 1971, Watchdogging public agencies, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Steering Committee letter re: lunch meeting, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - 5th Annual Conference (announcement), 1971 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Steering Committee letter, April 1974 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Preliminary proposal for 1974 meeting, October 1973 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Press release, Hartman citations, April 4, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Press release, PEO Conference, New York, April 7, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Policy statement PEO (2nd Annual Conference), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Blank sheets "News from ... PEO" (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - 6th Annual PEO announcement, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Master plan policies for the people, c. 1969 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Task Force on New York Critique, PEO 4th Annual Conference, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Press release, make-up of City Planning Committee, 1970, December 1970 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - PEO Archives (photos, buttons, embosser, etc.) (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Clarence Funnyé: The Man and His Views, c. 1970 (Box 3, Folder 68)